okay we are ready to tackle validation
which is pretty fun so if I switch over
to articles controller
this is where we left off the only
difference
is that I've added some doc locks to the
various methods this is a good habit to
get into
and locally if you do something like
peach be storm they can automate this
process
alright so let's head down to the store
method
this is what we need to focus on so if
you remember
in its current state we could submit
this form
and no error would be thrown we try it
and a new role has been entered into the
database table
and were echoing it out but there's
nothing there
this is a very bad thing so instead
we're gonna leverage
validation to ensure that the sorts of
things never happen
so let's tackle that now but real quick
let's do a select star from articles and
I'm getting to lead
from articles where the ID Eagle 7
just to start from scratch okay let's
get into it
now many show you two different ways to
handle this one
is through using what we call a former
Qwest class
an object this is really nice for more
complex validation
but you also have things where it's very
simple
you just wanna make sure that the user
does fill out a fielder to
and then you can continue and for those
situations
we can take advantage perpetrate that
where bill includes by default
so let's start with former quests as you
can imagine
we have a generator for that so higher
and peach PR dicen
and we scroll up you'll see this section
right here make
request now think these classes as a way
for the user
to make some kind of request for your
application
whether it's signing up or upgrading
their subscription
or in this case creating a new article
so what we try this out make a new
former Qwest
and we could call it create article or
publish article
or schedule whatever sorta terminology
your business uses
in this case a simple credit approach is
fine now a lot of people will
add request to the end as a suffix you
can do that
you can leave it off it's up to you will
keep it on here though
and that's it so now we will switch back
and if I open up ap HTTP
requests this is where those classes
will be added
man this looks a little confusing at
first but actually it's very
very simple so we have two different
methods here authorize
in roles the first one is Dez the user
have permission
to perform this kind of request or
action
here's an example what if somebody was
trying to
edit a comment that they didn't create
well
of course we don't want to allow that
John cannot
added a comment that was created by
chain this
is where we can and that sort of logic
now in our case we don't even really
have a membership system setup
somebody said that a true anyone can
make this request
currently next we have our rules
and this is where we can add our Terms
essentially
for the request for example if we go
back to article slash create
we have a title abadi in a published at
okay well we can reference those exact
names
title will be required next
the body will be required as well and
are published at
will be required as well but maybe
there's
other things we need to do as well for
example imagine you have a sign-up form
and your email field should be required
but it should also be
other specific type it should look like
an email address
and then maybe your name is required but
also it needs to be at least
two characters lock and if you want to
see a full massive list of what you can
do
go to learn how to calm slash stocks
slash
validation now what we had a couple more
we can either use the pipe here so I
could say required
and it should also be at that date tight
some notice we use a pipe to separate
them
or if you prefer you can use a general
array
either one works let's just stick with
the pipe for now
next for the title mostly just for fun
will say it needs to happen minimum
length
up three characters
how about that well I can say men
Colin and then the minimum value think
this has our argument
sonar case it should be at least 3
characters so we can represent it like
that
all rights and now we set up our
authorization
we've set up our validation rules let's
switch back to our controller
and now all we're gonna do is ty painted
right here
create article request and we'll call it
request okay so we can leave it like
this
or we can import the class at the top in
clean things up just a little bit
and then we will update our talk lock
cool
so now here's a very important concept
to understand
when we type hence this former Qwest
behind-the-scenes
lagerfeld's going to pick up on the fact
that we are dealing with validation here
and it will automatically trigger the
validation
before this method actually gets
executed that's really important to
understand
so in translation what that means
is the body this method one never fire
we won't ever create an article unless
our validation past now what happens if
it failed
well for example at the user doesn't
enter anything in the title
the validation fails this method never
gets fired
and instead we actually redirect to the
previous page
so that the user can try again okay so
before we tried this on the browser
let's go to the cycle once together the
user
comes to the create page: in the fill
out the various fields in the form
now when the form cements we prepare
to trigger this method however lagerfeld
picks up on the fact that we've tight
end to this object
and it's going to do its best to give us
that object
however in the process it will detect
that this object can be validated
so it triggers that validation
automatically for you
if validation passes it gives us a
request object
can we create the article however if
validation passes
once again this method never triggers
and we instead redirect to the previous
route
so that the user can correct them
stake from the form so now what I want
you to notice
is that with implemented validation
without adding
a single line to this method body so I
can remove that
next we are receiving the request
so we no longer need to use the facade I
can just save request
all and that would be equivalent which
means at the top
we can remove that import right there
okay
very clean so why don't we try this out
in the browser
and see if it works
we will they said article sash creates
in this time
we will enter thanks so answer entire
and the current eight is fine and the
article
and everything worked so no issues there
but this time
we're gonna try to submit the form
without feeling something and
let's leave the body plank okay one now
I add article and take a look
we didn't get redirected back to that
main page which is redirected
back to this form because the validation
failed
so that's what I mean when I say is all
sort of happens
automatically which is cool but we do
have one problem
if the user makes a mistake well we
didn't notify them what went wrong
so they really have no clue and as you
can imagine for a big form
this is a problem we need to get them
some feedback
so what we fix that we can do that by
returning
to our view in 10 we display any
validation errors
right below the form now here's the next
important thing for you to understand
your views were always have access to
and errors
variable so to demonstrate that if we
would have our top
errors list to see what would happen so
we visit the page
and right now you can see it's an ever
back we didn't have to create that
variable
or pass it to the view it was
automatically done Byler hell
right now its empty because we have no
validation errors
but if we do run s now take a look
we ran the validation it failed it
redirected back
it populated the airbag and now you can
see we have
to areas here so here's what we can do
we could say if week have any errors
this is nothing more than a helper
method but let us know
if we have any errors so if we do and we
landed at the bottom
then we want to display them one that we
use some bootstrap classes
alert an alert danger now
I can say if we have any errors then
fort
each error as error then
display ed with analysts item like so
and then finally
and for each and we're done create the
EC
so let's try this one more time we had
no errors
so we display nothing but next we try to
submit the form
and we do have a risk so you see them
listed here
and it looks like our CSS it a little
bit of but you get the basic idea
the important thing is that the user has
some feedback now
so maybe we fill out the title but we
leave the body plank
much at article now that works and
notice how the messages are dynamic
so let's say eight we fill up the body
we fill out a title
so we handled the required validation
rule but we don't have enough characters
remember we set a minimum length on now
and we run it
it will still fail in the message will
be updated accordingly
so once again let's properly form and
this and we'll publish it today and
after we add the article
everything worked so validation decision
that harden your cell
but let me show you one last thing to
finish up the lesson
we talked about former quests which are
pretty cool
they offer a nice clean dedicated place
to put this stuff
however if you don't wanna bother
creating a class
like I told you we can also call the
Validate method
directly on the controller let me show
you what this looks like
if we take a look at the parent class
and notice that we
import this straight called validates
request and specifically we have the
Validate method
where you give it your request you get
your rules and it was essentially
perform
in the exact same way so let's try this
out
this time we come back here and now
when I can use create article request
will just use where hells general
request so let me import that at the top
eliminate HTTP request
we'll update our doc block and now
we don't need a former Qwest we can just
call validate directly on the controller
we give it the request this will give us
the information
at the user typed into the form and then
we pass our validation rules
chest like we did before
right here so let's keep it very simple
title is required and body
is required
so like I said for basic stuff this is a
nice way to go
it's quick and fast alright so now let's
try this one out together
we will create a new article I'm gonna
leave this plank
in we should get the exact same thing
and we do
so it's up to you to decide when each
one is important
if you want you could always use upon
request and never call that validate met
another controller
some people would say it's not the
controller's job to handle that election
really once again it just depends upon
context
what's cool though is you can make up
your own mind on this
so what we're going to do in this case
since we already created eighty create
former Qwest
min and do a few steps and bring it back
to what we had before
okay so that looks good good job in the
next video
let's return to our views and talk a
little bit about partials
and how we can clean and dry up our code